<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<<<<<<< HEAD
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Janit Vora's Blog</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2020-04-07T11:29:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Cloud Workload Placement Strategy</title><link href="/articles/2020/04/07/cloud-workload-placement/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-04-07T11:29:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-07T11:29:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Janit Vora</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-04-07:/articles/2020/04/07/cloud-workload-placement/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Several factors go into determining the optimal workload placement strategy. Determining the best workload placement strategy is easy for greenfield projects or for start-ups. For mature enterprises who decide to move to the cloud, the workload placement strategy is based on the &lt;a href="https://www.janitvora.com/articles/2020/02/25/enterprise-cloud-adoption-strategy/" title="cloud adoption strategy"&gt;cloud adoption strategy&lt;/a&gt;. Based on the cloud adoption …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Several factors go into determining the optimal workload placement strategy. Determining the best workload placement strategy is easy for greenfield projects or for start-ups. For mature enterprises who decide to move to the cloud, the workload placement strategy is based on the &lt;a href="https://www.janitvora.com/articles/2020/02/25/enterprise-cloud-adoption-strategy/" title="cloud adoption strategy"&gt;cloud adoption strategy&lt;/a&gt;. Based on the cloud adoption strategy, the enterprise architect needs to conduct application profiling for all applications and determine their cloud migration strategy based on the models like &lt;a href="https://www.computerweekly.com/tip/Cloud-applications-Five-migration-tips-from-Gartner" title="Gartner's 5R model"&gt;Gartner's 5R model&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/enterprise-strategy/6-strategies-for-migrating-applications-to-the-cloud/" title="AWS' 6R model"&gt;AWS' 6R model&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attributes for Application Profiling:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An enterprise architect should focus on their organization's current portfolio to understand its technical landscape, challenges, and dependencies in order to determine the workload placement strategy. Criteria can vary from one organization to another, but the criteria should cover the following attributes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Architecture&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understand your application architecture in the context of its multiple components. This type of focus might result in you categorizing applications as monolithic with technical debt to be resolved. Levels of distribution and standardization might also drive the need to decompose and group workloads into manageable chunks of effort for cloud adoption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other important factors are stateful applications, applications that run on traditional systems, and determining the components to be replaced as applications are re-architected for cloud migration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, some workloads require less effort and can be moved as-is. Those workloads are usually stateless, standardized and have a microservices architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While determining the final outcome the enterprise architect should consider the full lifecycle of applications: from development to production support. Understanding and assessing all the environments of a workload and support structures is essential before determining the migration path of a workload.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Security and compliance&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The enterprise architect should be cognizant of all compliance requirements(PCI, GDPR etc.) related to the enterprise as they analyse the as-is landscape and prepare to vet cloud target options. It is important to establish plans which satisfy each compliance requirement associated with all workloads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Data&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another important consideration is data. Based on the criticality of the application and its data, it needs to be determined if the data wil be hosted on-premise, inside the UK, inside EU or global, what will be the data access mechanism and at what speeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Technology&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technical factors also help prioritize workloads for applications. An application which uses web containers to encapsulate business logic will require less effort to transform into a cloud solution as compared to a monolithic COBOL software. Hence the effort required to migrate to the cloud vis-a-vis the benefits it might bring needs to be considered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Dependencies&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All enterprise workloads are tightly knit in to the application landscape. Hence upstream and downstream dependencies need to be considered for each workload. Very few stand-alone workloads exist in an enterprise. All workloads are tightly or loosely coupled with key business and technical functions in an enterprise. It is important to analyze the impact of replacing or changing each workload to avoid unsuccessful cloud adoption attempts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Scalability&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cloud based applications should be inherently scalable. However, scalability requires a level of abstraction between application state, particular IP addresses, particular system calls and their underlying platforms. Some applications should be positioned to scale and take advantage of cloud capabilities like cloud bursting. To leverage the benefits of cloud computing, workloads which need scalability should be duly prioritized. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Output of Application Profiling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the attributes mentioned above, we can take a decision of what to do with a workload and do some Application Profiling for each workload. Workloads could be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Repurchased: Drop and Shop&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effectively, this is just a licensing change. Drop the on-premise application and shop a SaaS application on the cloud. This strategy is useful for legacy applications which need upgrade (Eg. Hosted CRM)  or legacy applications which are incompatible to the cloud(Eg. Telco Billing Software).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Rehosted: Lift and Shift:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This involves moving applications from on-premise hosting to cloud hosting without any changes being made to the application. Eg: Moving a website from on-premise hosting to AWS. To leverage this strategy, it is important to identify the right applications that can benefit from the cloud in their current form. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Replatformed: Lift, Tinker and Shift:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This strategy involves moving applications from on premise to the cloud by making some changes to these application to ensure cloud compatibility. The crucial factors while executing this strategy are to identify the right workloads for migration and extensive post migration testing and monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Re-factored/Re-Architected:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision to rearchitect an application is cost intensive and hence should be taken after proper cost benefit analysis. Critical applications which need to leverage cloud-native features such as development agility, scalability or performance are perfect candidates for rearchitecture usually to a microservices based architecture. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Retired:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applications which are identified as redundant or candidates for consolidation with other applications are retired. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Retained:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applications which could not be easily migrated to the cloud, but are critical from a strategic perspective will be retained. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://cloud.netapp.com/blog/aws-migration-strategy-the-6-rs-in-depth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Workload Placement Strategy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once enterprise architecture determines that a workload needs to be moved to the cloud, the next step is to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Determine the appropriate Cloud Service Model for that workload and &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Determine the appropriate Cloud Deployment Model for that workload
&lt;p align = "center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Cloud Workloads Model" src="/img/CloudWorkloadModels.png"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;How to determine Cloud Service Model?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p align = "center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Cloud Service Model" src="/img/CloudServiceModel.png"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;How to determine Cloud Deployment Model?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deployment model will also need to be assessed and determined for workloads. 
Deployment model assessment framework has the following attributes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cloud Service Providers: There are three major cloud providers: AWS: Amazon Web Services, Microsoft Azure and Google Cloud Portal. As discussed above in the &lt;a href="https://www.janitvora.com/articles/2020/02/25/enterprise-cloud-adoption-strategy/" title="enterprise cloud adoption strategy blog"&gt;enterprise cloud adoption strategy blog&lt;/a&gt; these three are the frontrunners for cloud computing since they have the scale, resilience and maturity to be able to host large enterprise workloads.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Geography: There are three tiers within which all data stored for an enterprise across its cloud platforms should fit: Local (Within the UK), Across Europe and Global. This could be implemented across private, public or hybrid cloud as per the size and scale of an enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data Classification: Data is usually classified as &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Secret: Available only to specific individuals,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Confidential: Available to selected groups,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Internal: Available to everyone within the organization and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Public: Available to everyone including the general public
&lt;p align = "center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Data Classification" src="/img/DataClassification.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
Irrespective of the classification and geography of where the data is stored, PCI and GDPR as well as any other applicable regulations should be strictly adhered to while designing the workload deployment architecture. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Service Tier:
&lt;p align = "center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Service Tier" src="/img/ServiceTier.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Important Architectural Principles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While deploying workloads on the cloud, some important architectural principles should be adhered to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data Workload Availability: Authentication mechanisms, access channels and systems should help provide access in-line with data criticality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data Workload Confidentiality: Should be implemented across the cloud workloads by ensuring that access is 'Least Privilege' so that right people have access to the data. Data should be encrypted at rest, in transit and in use. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data Workload Integrity: Should be achieved by protecting data from deletion or modification and ensuring that important lost data could also be recovered. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The level of abstraction provided across multiple clouds will depend on the cloud portability strategy of the enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Securing the network and minimizing attack surface&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Securing application workloads and workload integrations through appropriate authentication and authorization mechanisms&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step of workload placement is to conduct application profiling of existing applications in an enterprise and determine whether to repurchase, rehost, replatform, rearchitect, retain or retire existing applications. Based on the application profiling, an appropriate cloud service model and cloud deployment model is determined for each workload. The workload placement strategy of each workload is thus determined with due consideration to important architectural principles. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://www.ibm.com/garage/method/practices/discover/cloud-workload-assessment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/mw-1609-fernandes-trs/index.html&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://cloud.netapp.com/blog/aws-migration-strategy-the-6-rs-in-depth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/enterprise-strategy/6-strategies-for-migrating-applications-to-the-cloud/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://www.computerweekly.com/tip/Cloud-applications-Five-migration-tips-from-Gartner&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="cloud"></category><category term="cloud"></category><category term="technology"></category><category term="strategy"></category><category term="enterprise architecture"></category></entry><entry><title>Enterprise Cloud Documentation</title><link href="/articles/2020/03/28/enterprise-cloud-documentation/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-03-28T19:22:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-28T19:22:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Janit Vora</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-03-28:/articles/2020/03/28/enterprise-cloud-documentation/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Every Cloud implementation team or CoE team in an organization adopts a journey of moving from cloud strategy to implementation. Underpinning this journey is usually a bunch of artifacts - all of which help provide direction and support to the Cloud CoE teams.
&lt;img alt="Cloud Documentation" src="/img/Cloud_Documentation.jpg"&gt;
As shown in the diagram above, the strategy …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Every Cloud implementation team or CoE team in an organization adopts a journey of moving from cloud strategy to implementation. Underpinning this journey is usually a bunch of artifacts - all of which help provide direction and support to the Cloud CoE teams.
&lt;img alt="Cloud Documentation" src="/img/Cloud_Documentation.jpg"&gt;
As shown in the diagram above, the strategy and architecture team usually helps create artifacts such as strategy documents, Cloud Enterprise Architecture patterns, Tooling Patterns and Solution Patterns. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution patterns are usually based on inputs from the strategy documentation, EA patterns and project specific design pattern requirements. Solution patterns inform and help define project specific solution design documentation. Project specific solution design is usually created by cloud implementation project teams or Cloud CoE team. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project specific build and configuration related documentation will also be required for each implementation. This would also be a Cloud CoE/cloud implementation team responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="cloud"></category><category term="cloud"></category><category term="technology"></category><category term="strategy"></category><category term="enterprise architecture"></category></entry><entry><title>Enterprise Cloud Adoption Strategy</title><link href="/articles/2020/02/25/enterprise-cloud-adoption-strategy/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-02-25T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-25T09:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Janit Vora</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-02-25:/articles/2020/02/25/enterprise-cloud-adoption-strategy/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The objective of this post is to suggest activities required to be completed for Enterprise Architecture to help an organization embark on its cloud adoption journey.&lt;/p&gt;
=======
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Janit Vora's Blog</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2020-02-25T09:00:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Enterprise Cloud Adoption Strategy</title><link href="/articles/2020/02/25/enterprise-cloud-adoption-strategy/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-02-25T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-25T09:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Janit Vora</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-02-25:/articles/2020/02/25/enterprise-cloud-adoption-strategy/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The objective of this post is to suggest activities required to be completed for Enterprise Architecture to help an organization embark on its cloud adoption journey.&lt;/p&gt;
>>>>>>> origin/master
&lt;p&gt;I have used the long-form format since the intention is to inform and hence enable Enterprise Architecture. This encompasses the journey from determining the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The objective of this post is to suggest activities required to be completed for Enterprise Architecture to help an organization embark on its cloud adoption journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have used the long-form format since the intention is to inform and hence enable Enterprise Architecture. This encompasses the journey from determining the cloud strategy to creating a BAU cloud function within the enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scope of this guide is to help an organization’s enterprise architecture function make decisions on how to move its technology estate to the cloud. This guide describes the activities required, related decisions, challenges, risks and success factors for a successful journey to cloud computing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to define Enterprise Cloud Strategy?&lt;/h2&gt;
<<<<<<< HEAD
&lt;p&gt;&lt;p align = "center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="How to define an Enterprise Cloud Strategy?" src="/img/HowToDefineEnterpriseCloudStrategy.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
=======
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="How to define an Enterprise Cloud Strategy?" src="/img/HowToDefineEnterpriseCloudStrategy.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
>>>>>>> origin/master
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Inputs to Cloud Strategy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are different factors which influence Enterprise Cloud Strategy. These factors serve as inputs to the process of defining the cloud strategy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Business Strategy, Vision and Mission: IT strategy is informed by business strategy and hence vision and mission related to cloud adoption strategy should also be derived from the same.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inputs from ‘Application Portfolio Rationalization: ’Vision, mission, approach should also dovetail with any application portfolio rationalization programmes undertaken and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inputs from ‘IT Strategy and Technology Roadmap’: The overall IT strategy and technology roadmap of the enterprise will also inform the cloud strategy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inputs from ‘Cloud Maturity assessment’ might help determine the cloud maturity of an enterprise and could be another input to determining cloud strategy&lt;/li&gt;
<<<<<<< HEAD
&lt;li&gt;Enlisting the major reasons for cloud adoption - reasons which help answer 'Why Cloud?' will help determine the approach to cloud adoption. Some of the usual reasons for cloud adoption could be:
&lt;p align = "center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Reasons for using Cloud Strategy" src="/img/cloud-adoption-reasons.png"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
=======
&lt;li&gt;Enlisting the major reasons for cloud adoption - reasons which help answer 'Why Cloud?' will help determine the approach to cloud adoption. Some of the usual reasons for cloud adoption could be:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Reasons for using Cloud Strategy" src="/img/cloud-adoption-reasons.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
>>>>>>> origin/master
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Defining the Enterprise Cloud Strategy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the inputs, understanding of the technology stack and organizational priorities, decisions need to be made regarding various dimensions of the cloud strategy. There are multiple dimensions that need to be considered. I will try and discuss through an indicative list of all aspects which need to be considered to determine an enterprise cloud strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;1. Cloud Migration Strategy&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on organizational priorities, technology roadmap and portfolio rationalization recommendations, it needs to be determined as to what cloud strategy the organization should follow:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Aggressive Cloud Strategy&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Planned Cloud Strategy&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Reactive Cloud Strategy&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Try to position all applications to cloud first&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Conduct Cloud Suitability Assessment for the full application portfolio&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Based on APR assessment and technology strategy, initiate cloud migration for select existing and new applications&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;2. Hosting Approach&lt;/h4&gt;
<<<<<<< HEAD
&lt;p&gt;The hosting strategy for cloud adoption depends on an organization’s priorities. The most common approaches to hosting with their characteristics are described below:
&lt;p align = "center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Cloud Hosting Approach" src="/img/Hybrid_cloud_hosting.png"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;3. Cloud Tiers: How to choose between IaaS, PaaS and SaaS&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p align = "center"&gt;
![Choosing between IaaS, PaaS and SaaS, Source: Microsoft]({static}/img/HowToChooseIaaSPaaSSaaS.png)
&lt;/p&gt;

=======
&lt;p&gt;The hosting strategy for cloud adoption depends on an organization’s priorities. The most common approaches to hosting with their characteristics are described below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Cloud Hosting Approach" src="/img/Hybrid_cloud_hosting.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;3. Cloud Tiers: How to choose between IaaS, PaaS and SaaS&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Choosing between IaaS, PaaS and SaaS, Source: Microsoft" src="/img/HowToChooseIaaSPaaSSaaS.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
>>>>>>> origin/master
&lt;p&gt;An IaaS model provides maximum control as the figure above illustrates. It allows you full control over the operating system, and allows you to introduce secure concepts such as isolated VMs, secure boot, just-in-time access, etc. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PaaS increases this abstraction OS, middleware and runtime are also provided by the cloud vendor. PaaS components are architected to provide scalability and agility to support cloud applications. This is an evolution from IaaS which requires the architect or engineer to build the scalability and agility using traditional techniques at the infrastructure level, i.e. load balancers, traffic management, scale-sets, etc. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SaaS completes the models, whereby the platform provider (i.e. Microsoft) manages the entire stack and provisions access to the "software" as required by the users of the organisation. In this model, the organisation has a lot less control within the infrastructure and the application tier and instead places more trust in the vendor. Ultimately this is the cloud nirvana, as typically SaaS products are 'born in the cloud' and can usually be considered truly 'cloud native'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;4. How to choose the correct cloud implementation: Multi cloud, Hybrid Cloud or Private Cloud?&lt;/h4&gt;
<<<<<<< HEAD
&lt;p&gt;Multi cloud wins this hands down thanks to reasons ranging from vendor lock in, performance and latency, compliance across geographies and resilience. As seen below, multi cloud is the most popular approach to cloud globally. 
&lt;p align = "center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Enterprise Cloud Strategy" src="/img/MultiCloudAdoptionStats1.png"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
There are different reasons and different ways to use multi cloud as described below:
&lt;p align = "center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Multi cloud approach" src="/img/MulticloudStrategyStats2.png"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
Multi cloud is the dominant approach suggested for cloud services – especially for large enterprises which need to ensure compliance to various regulations. Single public cloud is useful for those looking to optimize costs whereas private cloud is a great option for those with especially stringent data security requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
=======
&lt;p&gt;Multi cloud wins this hands down thanks to reasons ranging from vendor lock in, performance and latency, compliance across geographies and resilience. As seen below, multi cloud is the most popular approach to cloud globally. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Enterprise Cloud Strategy" src="/img/MultiCloudAdoptionStats1.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are different reasons and different ways to use multi cloud as described below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Multi cloud approach" src="/img/MulticloudStrategyStats2.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multi cloud is the dominant approach suggested for cloud services – especially for large enterprises which need to ensure compliance to various regulations. Single public cloud is useful for those looking to optimize costs whereas private cloud is a great option for those with especially stringent data security requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
>>>>>>> origin/master
&lt;p&gt;Cloud management platforms such as Flexera (Rightscale), Scalr, Embotics, Morpheus Data etc. help manage multi cloud environments with ease. Here is &lt;a href="https://www.gartner.com/en/documents/3897466/magic-quadrant-for-cloud-management-platforms" title="Gartner’s magic quadrant report for Cloud Management Platforms"&gt;Gartner’s magic quadrant report for Cloud Management Platforms&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another recent, noteworthy development is &lt;a href="https://cloud.google.com/anthos" title="Google’s Anthos"&gt;Google’s Anthos&lt;/a&gt; – a Kubernetes based suite of GCP components that helps organisations to run applications on premises, on Google cloud and also to manage workloads on third-party clouds like AWS and Azure. This gives you ‘the freedom to deploy, run and manage your applications on the cloud of your choice, without requiring administrators and developers to learn different environments and APIs.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;5. Which Public Cloud Provider?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After zeroing in on the multi-cloud approach, we need to decide which cloud providers should we choose to go with. While workload placement strategy might help determine the best fit cloud for each individual workload, AWS, Ms Azure and GCP are the usual suspects for most cloud implementations.&lt;/p&gt;
<<<<<<< HEAD
&lt;p&gt;AWS had stolen a march over the competition, but Azure is catching up fast as the data from Rightscale's reports show below:
&lt;p align = "center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Public Cloud Adoption" src="/img/publiccloudadoption.png"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
Here is another comparison chart from Spiceworks’&lt;a href="https://community.spiceworks.com/blog/3208-public-cloud-trends-in-2019-and-beyond" title="Public Cloud Trends in 2019 and Beyond"&gt;Public Cloud Trends in 2019 and Beyond&lt;/a&gt; survey with responses from the users of AWS, Ms Azure and GCP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align = "center"&gt;
![AWS vs Ms Azure vs Google Cloud]({static}/img/AWSvsAzurevsGCP.png)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AWS is the oldest, most well-known and feature rich of all public cloud providers. It also has the largest community of users. This usually makes it the first choice for most cloud adoption programmes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;6. Challenges, Risks, Controls implemented&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Cloud Controls Matrix created by the Cloud Security Alliance is the best and only meta-framework of cloud-specific security controls. These controls which span across the enterprise are mapped to leading standards, best practices and regulations. CCM provides organizations with the needed structure, detail and clarity relating to information security tailored to cloud computing. CCM is currently considered a de-facto standard for cloud security assurance and compliance. The current version of the CCM is v3.0.1.
&lt;p align = "center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="CCM V3.0.1 Domains" src="/img/CCMv3.0.1Domains.png"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
An architect can leverage the &lt;a href="https://cloudsecurityalliance.org/artifacts/cloud-controls-matrix-v3-0-1/" title="CCM v3.0.1"&gt;CCM v3.0.1&lt;/a&gt; and tailor it to their organization.&lt;/p&gt;
=======
&lt;p&gt;AWS had stolen a march over the competition, but Azure is catching up fast as the data from Rightscale's reports show below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Public Cloud Adoption" src="/img/publiccloudadoption.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is another comparison chart from Spiceworks’&lt;a href="https://community.spiceworks.com/blog/3208-public-cloud-trends-in-2019-and-beyond" title="Public Cloud Trends in 2019 and Beyond"&gt;Public Cloud Trends in 2019 and Beyond&lt;/a&gt; survey with responses from the users of AWS, Ms Azure and GCP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="AWS vs Ms Azure vs Google Cloud" src="/img/AWSvsAzurevsGCP.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AWS is the oldest, most well-known and feature rich of all public cloud providers. It also has the largest community of users. This usually makes it the first choice for most cloud adoption programmes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;6. Challenges, Risks, Controls implemented&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Cloud Controls Matrix created by the Cloud Security Alliance is the best and only meta-framework of cloud-specific security controls. These controls which span across the enterprise are mapped to leading standards, best practices and regulations. CCM provides organizations with the needed structure, detail and clarity relating to information security tailored to cloud computing. CCM is currently considered a de-facto standard for cloud security assurance and compliance. The current version of the CCM is v3.0.1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="CCM V3.0.1 Domains" src="/img/CCMv3.0.1Domains.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An architect can leverage the &lt;a href="https://cloudsecurityalliance.org/artifacts/cloud-controls-matrix-v3-0-1/" title="CCM v3.0.1"&gt;CCM v3.0.1&lt;/a&gt; and tailor it to their organization.&lt;/p&gt;
>>>>>>> origin/master
&lt;h4&gt;7. Critical Enablers to define Enterprise Cloud Strategy&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Enterprise Cloud Strategy will need enablers listed below to be implemented successfully:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workload Placement Strategy: Define a framework using which the organization can place workloads quickly, securely and in line with relevant regulations. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Portability Strategy: Define guidelines to ensure that an application is portable between cloud providers. This is essential to ensure success of the multi-cloud strategy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exit Strategy: Create a document which provides guidance and direction to the organization to identify contingencies and create an exit plan for every application placed on the cloud.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cloud Service Deployment Standards: Ensure that every application hosted on cloud infrastructure are evaluated for and adhere to service deployment standards.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;8. Target State&lt;/h4&gt;
<<<<<<< HEAD
&lt;p&gt;Determining the Target State for an organization's technology estate will help drive the cloud adoption strategy. Here is a sample target state. The target state will help manage lots of complex apps in a flexible manner at a low cost.
&lt;p align = "center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Target State" src="/img/TargetState_New.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;9. Goals, Benefits and Measuring Success&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good Enterprise Cloud Strategy should define the goals that it needs to achieve, the benefits it should accrue to the organization and the method to measure these benefits. The goals should be well defined, clearly articulated and time bound. Goals could be across different areas and should differ as cloud maturity increases in the organization. A few sample goals for the beginning of an Enterprise's cloud journey are:
&lt;p align = "center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Goals" src="/img/Goals.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
=======
&lt;p&gt;Determining the Target State for an organization's technology estate will help drive the cloud adoption strategy. Here is a sample target state. Applications are segregated as systems of records, channel applications, enterprise functions and systems of integration based on their functions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Target State" src="/img/TargetState.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;9. Goals, Benefits and Measuring Success&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good Enterprise Cloud Strategy should define the goals that it needs to achieve, the benefits it should accrue to the organization and the method to measure these benefits. The goals should be well defined, clearly articulated and time bound. Goals could be across different areas and should differ as cloud maturity increases in the organization. A few sample goals for the beginning of an Enterprise's cloud journey are:
&lt;img alt="Goals" src="/img/Goals.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
>>>>>>> origin/master
&lt;h4&gt;10. Cloud Governance Strategy&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A cloud governance board should be established on the lines of EA governance boards. The cloud governance board should have representatives from all areas of the enterprise. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cloud governance board, as its name suggests will be responsible for governing cloud adoption in the enterprise. The board will have to convene regularly in the initial days of cloud adoption with their focus on functions such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cloud Advisory: Advising any business area(s) on cloud adoption&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cloud Feasibility: Reviewing the feasibility and risks related to cloud migration proposals from each business area&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cloud Approval: Approving the cloud adoption proposal(s)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cloud governance board should be supported by the technical cloud advisory. The technical cloud advisory should be a sub-group of the cloud governance board with members who understand cloud technology and can advise the cloud governance board on complicated issues related to the cloud. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A well defined Enterprise Cloud Strategy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an end product of the exercise, the cloud strategy should communicate the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define an approach to cloud adoption and key decisions made regarding the same&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define a Target State for Cloud Adoption&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;List the Goals and related Key Success Factors for cloud adoption&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;List activities, foreseeable risks, challenges and controls adopted for the cloud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define a Target Operating Model for the BAU cloud function&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="cloud"></category><category term="cloud"></category><category term="technology"></category><category term="strategy"></category><category term="enterprise architecture"></category></entry></feed>